James A. Woodburn papers, 1876-1983 C83
Indiana University Archives
James A. Woodburn papers
1876-1983
1880-1940
Indiana University Archives
Woodburn, James Albert, 1856-1943
C83
3.4 cubic feet 4 boxes
James A. Woodburn was a long time professor of history at Indiana University. The collection consists of the correspondence, personal items, and publications of James A. Woodburn and is organized into four series.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Biographical Note
James Albert Woodburn was born on November 30, 1856 in a two-story brick house on North College Street in Bloomington, Indiana, to James W. Woodburn and Martha Jane Hemphill Woodburn. At the time of James' birth, his father, James W. Woodburn, was serving as principal of the Preparatory department at Indiana University.
James A. Woodburn was educated in the Bloomington Public school system before entering Indiana University in 1872. He earned his A.B. degree in 1876 and soon after began teaching at a public school in Richland Township, Rush County, Indiana, before moving on to become an assistant principal in the Grayville, Illinois, public schools. In 1879 he returned to Bloomington where he began teaching Latin and advanced Mathematics at the Indiana University Preparatory school. While employed as an instructor at the Preparatory school, Woodburn worked towards an A.M. degree in History that he completed in 1885. Starting in 1886, Woodburn secured consecutive leaves of absence from his teaching responsibilities at I.U. to enroll at John Hopkins University in Baltimore, Maryland in pursuit of a Ph.D. degree in History. While working toward his Ph.D. degree he taught Rhetoric and Composition at John Hopkins University and, during his absence, was also named Associate Professor of American History at I.U. in 1888.
After graduation, in 1890, he returned to Bloomington and joined the faculty at Indiana University as a professor of American History and Politics. While giving lectures at the University Extension division in Indianapolis he met Caroline Louise Gelston who had been teaching in Miss Sewall's Classical school. The two were married in Ann Arbor, Michigan, on November 20, 1893 and the couple soon afterward moved to Bloomington. A little over a year later, on November 30, 1894 James and Caroline's first son, James Gelston, was born followed by the couple's only daughter, Janet McMillan, who was born in 1900. The couple also had another son, Edward Albert, who was born on July 26, 1903. He died in infancy at the age of ten weeks.
Woodburn's responsibilities at I.U. changed in 1914 when the department of History was split from the department of Political Science to form two separate, autonomous departments with Woodburn serving as the first chair of the new department. This appointment was a landmark achievement for Woodburn being that he was one of the first men in America to hold such a prestigious chair. Woodburn remained an instructor at I.U. until the 1920-21 academic year when he gave up teaching to become a research professor. He retired from the university in 1924. After his retirement he was named professor emeritus. As an acknowledgement of his contributions to the Indiana University community, was awarded an honorary L.L.D. degree in 1926.
While teaching at I.U. Woodburn received some noteworthy accolades for his academic endeavors such as being awarded the John Marshall Prize from John Hopkins University for best volume in political science in 1903 and later, in 1909, being awarded an honorary L.L.D. degree from Colgate University. Woodburn is also credited with being a charter member of the Phi Beta Kappa Society at I.U. which is a highly prestigious undergraduate honors organization.
One of his most memorable contributions Woodburn made to Indiana University was the publication of his "History of Indiana University" in 1940. Prompted by then President William Lowe Bryan, Woodburn spent years researching the history of the university. The publication of the history was of such great monumental importance to the academic community in Bloomington that an elaborate testimonial banquet was held on November 30, 1940 to honor Woodburn. This event was also planned to coincide with Woodburn's 84th birthday. During the celebration Woodburn formally presented a copy of the "History of Indiana University" to then president, Herman B Wells, who accepted it on behalf of the University.
Aside from his duties at Indiana University Woodburn served in the position of visiting professor at the University of Wisconsin, University of Chicago, Leland Stanford University, University of Michigan, Cornell University, and Washington State College. His many scholarly memberships included the American Historical Association, American Political Science Association, Indiana Historical Society, Indianapolis Literary Club, Kiwanis Club, National Arts Club, as well as many others.
On December 12, 1943, James A. Woodburn died of pneumonia in Madison, Wisconsin and was buried at the Rose Hill cemetery in Bloomington.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: 1) Correspondence 2) Personal Items 3) Publications, Galleys & Transcripts, sub-series: History of IU, sub-series: Books and articles, sub-series: Collected publications 4) Testimonial Banquet, sub-series: Speeches, sub-series: News clippings, sub-series: Correspondence.
Scope and Content Note
The Correspondence series primarily consists of letters written to James A. Woodburn by friends and colleagues. Significant correspondents include George Ade, Walter Q. Gresham, Benjamin Harrison, David Starr Jordan, Daniel Kirkwood, Meredith Nicholson, James W. Riley, T. C. Steele, and Frederick Jackson Turner. At the end of this series is a folder of two indexes that list Woodburn's correspondents in alphabetical order as well as the dates of the separate letters.
The Personal items series contains one of Woodburn's report cards from when he was in his final year at IU, a class grade book from when he taught American History and Politics at IU, and a program from a slide show.
The Publications, galleys & transcripts series has been separated into three subseries. The first subseries, History of Indiana University, consists of the transcript, book jacket, announcement of publication, notes and outlines, and the published copy of History of Indiana University. The second subseries, Books and Articles, contains Woodburn's publications. The third subseries, Collected Publications, includes publications written by anyone other than Woodburn.
The Testimonial Banquet series consists of program materials, speeches delivered during the banquet, related news clippings, and related correspondence. This banquet was held on November 30, 1920 to celebrate Woodburn's 84th birthday and the publication of the "History of Indiana University."
Related Material
For related materials please see the Woodburn family collection, Collection C91.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 9361, 0555, 0617, and 2008/031.
History of Indiana University.; Higher education in Indiana.; Woodburn family; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Archives; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931 -- Correspondence; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Correspondence; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931 -- Correspondence -- Selections; Woodburn, James Albert, 1856-1943 -- Archives; Woodburn, James Albert, 1856-1943 -- Correspondence; Woodburn, James Albert, 1856-1943 -- History of Indiana University; Woodburn, James Albert, 1856-1943 -- Higher education in Indiana; Steele, T. C. (Theodore Clement), 1847-1926 -- Correspondence; Steele, T. C. (Theodore Clement), 1847-1926 -- Correspondence -- Selections; Gresham, Walter Quintin, 1832-1895 -- Correspondence; Gresham, Walter Quintin, 1832-1895 -- Correspondence -- Selections; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901 -- Correspondence; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901 -- Correspondence -- Selections
- Correspondence, 1882-1942
  - Adams, E. D., 16 Sep 1908 (Box 1)
  - Ade, George, 20 Nov 1917 (Box 1)
  - Angell, James B., 4 Dec 1894 (Box 1)
  - Banta, David. D., 9 Feb 1889 (Box 1)
  - Beveridge, Albert J., 12 Mar 1902 - 5 Feb 1927 (Box 1)
  - Biddle, Ward G., 4 Feb 1932-24 March 1936, undated (Box 1)
  - Boisen, Anton. T., 25 May 1915 (Box 1)
  - Bowers, Claude G., 29 June 1925-24 Dec 1925 (Box 1)
  - Breckenridge, Sophonisba P., 18 Dec 1907 (Box 1)
  - Bright, Michael S., 5 Nov 1922 (Box 1)
  - Brooks, Robert C., 3 May 1914 (Box 1)
  - Bross, Ernest, 20 Oct 1916 - 30 Mar 1919 (Box 1)
  - Bryan, Elmer Burritt, 16 Jun 1933 (Box 1)
  - Bryan, William J., 9 Jun 1900 (See also: Bryan, William Lowe) (Box 1)
  - Bryan, William Lowe, 30 Jun 1914 - 13 Jun 1932 (See also: Bryan, William J.) (Box 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 11 Dec 1931 (Box 1)
  - Carpenter, Charles T., 24 Nov 1938 (Box 1)
  - Carter, Gerry William?, 28 Jan 1891 (Box 1)
  - Chaney, John C., 26 Mar 1906 (Box 1)
  - Clarke, Grace Julian, 12 Dec 1902 (Box 1)
  - Clay, John C., 29 Dec 1891 (Box 1)
  - Craig, Will H., 28 May 1928 (Box 1)
  - Cravens, John W.? "JWC, 25 Jul 1914 (Box 1)
  - Cross, Arthur Lyon, 3 Jun 1934 (Box 1)
  - Day, Katherine Huntington, 6 Jan (Box 1)
  - Dewey, Davis R., 23 Dec 1932 (Box 1)
  - Douglas, Paul H., 16 Mar 1933 (Box 1)
  - Dowden, S., 27 May 1941 (Box 1)
  - Ely, Richard T., 27 Mar 1934 (Box 1)
  - Faris, J. C. K., 7 Apr 1915 (Box 1)
  - Finley, John, 3 Jan 1910 (Box 1)
  - Fisher, F. B., 29 May 1934 (Box 1)
  - Fletcher, E. R., 17 Nov 1929 (Box 1)
  - F, 12 Aug 1933 (Box 1)
  - Gipson, Lawrence H., 21 Mar 1917 - 3 Apr 1917 (Box 1)
  - Goodrich, James P., 9 Jan 1917 (Box 1)
  - Gresham, Walter. Q., 11 Apr 1888 - 13 Jun 1893 (Box 1)
  - G, 28 May 1918-11 May 1926 (Box 1)
  - Hunley, J., 12 Jan 1905 - 14 Dec 1906 (Box 1)
  - Harrison, Benjamin, 18 Mar 1882 - 28 May 1888 (Box 1)
  - Harwood, Samuel E., 25 Dec 1915 (Box 1)
  - Haskell, Henry J., 5 Sep 1903 - 19 Sep 1903 (Box 1)
  - Haskins, Charles H., 16 Apr 1892 - 1 Nov 1913 (Box 1)
  - Holland, Ernest, 26 Apr 1933 - 28 Apr 1933 (Box 1)
  - Hull, Charles H., 11 Jul 1908 (Box 1)
  - Hull, William J., 12 Feb 1934 (Box 1)
  - H, 11 Mar 1901 - 11 May 1926 (Box 1)
  - Jameson, J. F., 3 Nov 1911 - 18 Apr 1934 (Box 1)
  - Jenkinson, Issac, 16 Mar 1903 (Box 1)
  - Jordan, David S., 26 Oct 1886 (Box 1)
  - Julian, Mrs. W.?, 4 Feb 1896 (Box 1)
  - Kirkwood, Daniel, 4 Dec 1891 (Box 1)
  - La Follette, Robert W., 26 Feb 1910 (Box 1)
  - Lutz, Philip A., 1 Jan 1912 (Box 1)
  - Mabie, Hamilton W., 19 Dec 1889 (Box 1)
  - Macy, U. L., 25 Nov 1920 (Box 1)
  - Macy, Jesse, 24 Jul 1908 (Box 1)
  - Matthews, Claude, 15 Jun 1896 (Box 1)
  - McElroy, Robert M., 12 Feb 1918 (Box 1)
  - McNary, William P., 30 May 1918 (Box 1)
  - McQuiston, Raymer, 4 Jun 1934 (Box 1)
  - Mead, Edwin D., 21 Mar 1914 (Box 1)
  - Meany, Edmond S., 2 Apr 1904 (Box 1)
  - Miller, Hugh T., 17 Mar 1908 (Box 1)
  - Morse, Anson D., 2 Jan 1899 (Box 1)
  - Murdock, Victor, 5 Nov 1915 (Box 1)
  - McMarty, John B.?, 18 May 1904 (Box 1)
  - New, Harry S., 21 Apr 1908 (Box 1)
  - Nicholson, Meredith, 30 Jun 1913 - 27 Apr 1917 (Box 1)
  - Oxman, G. Bromley, 28 May 1934 (Box 1)
  - Quaife, M. M., 4 May 1928 (Box 1)
  - Riley, James Whitcomb, 12 Oct 1915 (Box 1)
  - Rosewater, Victor, 20 Jul 1934 (Box 1)
  - Ross, E. A., 27 Feb 1934 (Box 1)
  - R, 23 Oct 1894 - 8 Feb 1932 (Box 1)
  - Salmon, Lucy M., 4 Jan 1892 (Box 1)
  - Schurz, Carl, 7 Dec 1899 (Box 1)
  - Shotwell, James T., 27 Sep 1917 - 29 May 1934 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Matthew, 10 May 1924 (Box 1)
  - Smith, P., 26 Mar 1912 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Ulysses Howe, 13 Jul 1914 - 23 Jul 1914 (Box 1)
  - Smyth, Newman, 4 April 1927 (Box 1)
  - Sollitt, Ralph, 1 Aug 1918 (Box 1)
  - Surber, Charles P., 1916 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    (Correspondence regarding The New Purchase.)
  - Steele, T. C., 27 May 1904 - 28 May 1904 (Box 1)
  - Stillman, J. M., 2 Jul 1908 (Box 1)
  - de Sumichrast, F. C., 14 Apr 1917 (Box 1)
  - Turner, Frederick J., 2 Apr 1903 (Box 1)
  - Wait-Howe, Daniel, 9 Mar 1915 - 21 Jun ? (Box 1)
  - Watson, James E., 15 Jan 1907 (Box 1)
  - Weeks, Stephen B., 28 Nov 1912 (Box 1)
  - Whisenand, J. D., 17 Dec 1882 (Box 1)
  - Wickersham, G., 24 Jan 1933 (Box 1)
  - Wickware, Francis G., 6 Apr 1912 - 8 Apr 1915 (Box 1)
  - Willoughby, W. W., 29 Jan 1934 (Box 1)
  - Wilson, George Grafton, 16 April 1923 (Box 1)
  - Woodward, M. Josie, 18 Apr 1883 (Box 1)
  - Wynn, Frank B., 3 Dec 1912 (Box 1)
  - Woodburn, James A., 28 Mar 1906 - 29 Sep 1942 (Box 1)
  - Indexes of correspondence, 1882-1942 (Box 1)
- Personal items, 1876-1932
  - Report Card, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Program from slide show, 14 Apr 1911 (Box 1)
  - Class Book, 1914 (Box 1)
  - The Woodburn Room, Plaque of Dedication, 13 June 1932 (Box 1)
- Publications, galleys & transcripts, 1891-1957
  - History of Indiana University, 30 Nov 1940-1957
    - Announcement of publication of History of Indiana University, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Galleys for History of Indiana University,1820-1902, ca. 1940 (Box 1)
      General
      6 folders
    - History of Indiana University Volume I, 1940 (Box 1)
    - History of Indiana University book jacket, 1940 (Box 1)
    - History of Indiana University publication cost, copies, & picture sources, 30 Nov 1940 - 26 Sep 1957 (Box 1)
    - Notes & Outline on History of Indiana University, undated (Box 1)
    - Transcripts of History of Indiana University Chapters XV - XVII, 1820 - 1902 (Box 1)
      3 folders
  - Books and articles, 1883-1936
    - Woodburn, James A. (Box 2)
      - On Reading Indiana Student p. 156-158, (1883) (Box 2)
      - Higher Education in Indiana, Bureau of Education Circular of Information, No. 10, (1891) (Box 2)
      - Causes of the American Revolution John Hopkins University Studies in Historical and Political Science, 10th series, (1892) (Box 2)
      - The Historical Significance of the Missouri Compromise, (1894) (Box 2)
        2 books
      - American Oration, (1896) (Box 2)
        5 books
      - Washington's Foreign Policy and the Philippines The Independent p. 1170-1172, (27 Oct 1898) (Box 2)
      - The American Republic, (1903) (Box 2)
      - Amending the Constitution The Independent p. 1497-1501, (30 Dec 1909) (Box 2)
      - Scotch-Irish Presbyterians in Monroe County, Indiana, (1910) (Box 2)
      - Indiana History and Its Celebration Indiana Magazine of History, (Sept 1913) (Box 2)
      - The Life of Thaddeus Stevens, (1913) (Box 2)
      - Local Life and Color in the New Purchase Indiana Magazine of History Bulletin p. 215-233, (Dec 1913) (Box 2)
      - Politics and the Pulpit Ministerial Association, Indianapolis, reprinted from Indiana University Alumni Quarterly, (1915) (Box 2)
      - Foundations of the Commonwealth Celebration of the One Hundredth Anniversary of Indiana's Admission Into the Union p. 16-29, (11 Dec 1916) (Box 2)
      - The Indiana Centennial, (1916) (Box 2)
      - The New Purchase, (1916) (Box 2)
      - America and the War reprint from January Alumni Quarterly, (1918) (Box 2)
      - Promotion of Historical Study in America Following the Civil War reprint from Transactions of the Illinois State Historical Society, (1922) (Box 2)
      - Nationalism and Humanity Corda Fratres Review p. 2-6, (Nov 1923) (Box 2)
      - The American Community, (1924) (Box 2)
      - Political Parties and Party Problems in the United States Third Revised and Enlarged Edition, (1924) (Box 2)
      - Since the Beginning: a Retrospect reprint from Indiana University Alumni Quarterly, (July 1924) (Box 2)
      - The University and the War on War The John Hopkins Alumni Magazine p. 210-221, (1924) (Box 2)
      - The Makers of America, (1925) (Box 2)
      - The Constitution of Indiana, (1926) (Box 2)
      - History Teaching and International Relations Indiana History Bulletin p. 60-67, (10-11 Dec 1926) (Box 2)
      - Introduction to American History, (1926) (Box 2)
      - Pioneer Presbyterians in Indiana Presbyterianism in Indiana p. 24-40, (1926) (Box 2)
      - Western Radicalism in American Politics, reprint from The Mississippi Valley Historical Review, Vol XIII, (1926) (Box 2)
      - Beginners History of the United States, (1927) (Box 2)
      - Active Citizenship, (1928) (Box 3)
      - The Citizen and the Republic, (1928) (Box 3)
      - Elementary American History and Government, (1928) (Box 3)
      - Indiana Historical Society: A Hundred Years Centennial Handbook Indiana Historical Society p. 5-42, (1930) (Box 3)
      - Lucius Burris Swift Indiana Magazine of History p. 1-11, (March 1930) (Box 3)
      - Our United States, (1930) (Box 3)
      - Henry Smith Lane Indiana Magazine of History p. 279-287, (Dec 1931) (Box 3)
      - Our United States, (1931) (Box 3)
      - Historic Background of Our United States, (1932) (Box 3)
      - Early America, (1934) (Box 3)
      - A Noteworthy University Seminary in History: Reminiscences and Personalities reprint from John Hopkins Alumni Magazine, (1934) (Box 3)
      - Our United States, (1934) (Box 3)
      - United Presbyterian Beginnings reprint from Indiana Magazine of History, (March 1934) (Box 3)
      - Woodburn History: Some Generations of a Family, 1936; 3 Copies (Box 3)
  - Collected publications (other authors), 1925-1940
    - Old Bloomington, 1925 (Box 3)
    - Envelope of Chapter Proofs, ca. 1940 (Box 3)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, undated (Box 3)
    - Town & Gown by Dr. J. E. P. Holland, undated (Box 3)
    - Tribute to Dr. Woodburn by John W. Cravens, undated (Box 3)
    - The Making of the Constitution. A Syllabus, 1898 (Box 3)
    - The University & the Prosperity of Bloomington, undated (Box 3)
    - U.S. Senate Endorsement, 27 Oct 1926 (Box 3)
  - History of Indiana University Publication Correspondence, 1929-1956
    - Bryan, William Lowe, 17 Jun 1929 - 4 Jun 1936 (Box 3)
    - Chamness, Ivy L., 11 Dec 1939 - 13 Jun 1941 (Box 3)
    - Jordan, Harold W., 14 Mar 1940 - 30 Jun 1942 (Box 3)
    - Sims, Earl, 24 Apr 1945 - 7 Nov 1956 (Box 3)
- Testimonial Banquet, 1940-1983
  - General files, 1940-1983
    - Attendees (Box 4)
    - Program materials (Box 4)
    - Woodburn materials given to Alumni Office, 4 Jun 1983 (Box 4)
  - Speeches, 30 Nov 1940
    - Biddle, Ward G. (Box 4)
    - Houghton, John Woodburn (Box 4)
    - Kohlmeier, A. L. (Box 4)
    - Wells, Herman B (Box 4)
    - Woodburn, James A. (Box 4)
  - News clippings, 19 Nov 1940- 3 Dec 1940
    - News clippings with citations, 19 Nov 1940- 3 Dec 1940 (Box 4)
    - News clippings without citations, undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 13 Nov 1940- 28 Jan 1941
    - Congratulatory letters, A - W, 16 Nov 1940- 28 Jan 1941 (Box 4)
    - Congratulatory telegrams, A - W, 26 Nov 1940- 30 Nov 1940 (Box 4)
    - RSVP regrets with congratulatory note, A - H, 13 Nov 1940 - 10 Jan 1941 (Box 4)
    - RSVP regrets with congratulatory note, I - W, 18 Nov 1940 - 26 Dec 1940 (Box 4)